<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Manuel Ohlendorf</title>
    <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Manuel Ohlendorf</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© 2017 Manuel Ohlendorf. All rights reserved.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 20:11:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharing secrets with pass</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/009_sharing_secrets_with_pass/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 20:11:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/009_sharing_secrets_with_pass/</guid>
      <description>I don&amp;rsquo;t like password managers. I don&amp;rsquo;t trust them. But when you work in a small team and use a lot of different servers and technologies you sometimes have to securely store and share a secret with them. There are a lot of password managers out there that can do that but I want a very simple command line tool that just uses standard technologies and — Tata — Pass, the standard unix password manager hits the spot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The crazy date/time formatting in Go</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/008_go_time_format/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 09:34:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/008_go_time_format/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Formatting and parsing date/time strings is a very common use-case in programming. A lot of the programming languages I worked with take the same approach for that: Using the Unicode time pattern syntax &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr35/#Date_Format_Patterns&#34;&gt;UTS #35&lt;/a&gt;. For me it is always hard to remember the details, especially when it comes to the upper and lower case codes.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Material Design Buttons with AppCompat</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/007_material_design_buttons/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2015 10:21:06 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/007_material_design_buttons/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With the new release v23.0.0 of the AppCompat library it is now possible to create Material Design Buttons for Lollipop and Pre-Lollipop devices.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Hugo as the new static site generator</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/005_new_generator/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2015 08:45:58 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/005_new_generator/</guid>
      <description>Four years since my last blogpost and a very crappy old style of the site, I have decided completely revamp it.
My first thoughts were: You need a new static site generator and it has to be written in your favourite programming language (for now, this is JavaScript). After some googling and tinkering I came to a very different conclusion: Not the programming language or the features of the generator are important to me, but the available themes!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Curriculum Vitae</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2014 11:14:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/cv/</guid>
      <description>Technical Expertise  Languages Java, JavaScript, ObjectiveC, Swift, Python, Haskell Databases MongoDB, MySQL, PostgreSQL, RethinkDB Frameworks J2EE, Spring Boot, Android SDK, Django, AngularJS, NodeJS Concepts OOD, Unit, Module, and Systems Testing, OpenID, REST/SOAP, JSON, SEO/SEM, AJAX Software Intellij IDEA, Maven, Jenkins, Sonar, git, Apache, nginx Systems Mac, Linux, Windows (well, if I have to...)   Professional Experience  Software Architect, BDE Software Services GmbH March 2016 - present Hamburg, Germany Consulting work and software development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>L-System parser with Jangaroo</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/004_lsystem_parser_with_jangaroo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Mar 2011 16:44:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/004_lsystem_parser_with_jangaroo/</guid>
      <description>Have you ever heard of Jangaroo? It is an ActionScript&amp;reg;-to-Javascript compiler. It&#39;s an open-source project with an implementation of the Flash&amp;reg; API and the whole toolchain every programmer likes: Maven dependency management, good IDE support, TDD with JooUnit (a port of FlexUnit) and a lot more. It even comes with a declarative UI language EXML (well, it is quite similar to MXML), that can be used to generate ExtJS applications. For about a year I am now also helping to evolve Jangaroo and its toolchain.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baubericht Amati Shamrock - Tag 1</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/003_shamrock_tag_1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jan 2011 20:09:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/003_shamrock_tag_1/</guid>
      <description>Dies ist der erste Teil eines Bauberichts des Bausatzes Shamrock von Amati im Maßstab von 1:80. Da ich ein blutiger Anfänger bin, was Schiffsmodellbau angeht, ist dieser Bausatz genau das Richtige, denn der Rumpf ist ein vorgefertigtes Resinteil. So fängt das echte Modellbauen erst bei dem Deck an. Der Bausatz ist eigentlich auf italienisch, es liegt aber ein Zettel mit den wichtigsten Übersetzungen bei - so lernt man auch gleich noch etwas Fremdsprache, z.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting a Blogofile Blog on GitHub with GitHub Pages</title>
      <link>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/001_blogofile_on_github/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Dec 2010 13:09:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://manuel-ohlendorf.de/posts/001_blogofile_on_github/</guid>
      <description>So, in my first blog post I will describe howto use GitHub to serve a Blogofile Blog, which I have done with this blog. ### First, what is Blogofile? Blogofile is a framework for static websites. You don&amp;rsquo;t need a webserver and no database, only webspace. Blogofile provides templates, controllers and filters, almost like any other dynamic web frameworks and compiles them to a static website. Right now it is more or less a blogging engine but you can actually create any website you want.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>